hello it's June 8 2023 this is an update
from the active inference ontology
project at the Active inference
Institute this video is going to cover
what the active inference ontology is
now and a few of the ways that we're
using it a little bit about the roadmap
and plans for the ontology and
especially areas you can contribute if
you're interested to learn and apply
active inference and also to leverage
your learning and contributions so first
what is the active inference ontology
well at the public website you'll find
currently that for the set of terms
which constitute the active inference
ontology we have definitions
translations and correct and incorrect
examples there's often a lot of
unnecessary or excessive uncertainty
about what different terms mean in the
active inference field and so what the
active inference does ontology does is
first create a curated list of core
terms currently 64 four of them most of
which have an absolutely everyday
natural language definition
also we have several hundred extra
supplemental and entailed terms that
give us more comprehensive coverage of
the literature these terms and their
definitions help people speak the active
infant ontology and thus build your
fluency
we also have translations into many
languages so if you see a language here
that you know and you wanna
build Bridges between that language
community and the primarily English
active inference
literature
whether in education or research that's
a super important way that we can
improve the accessibility and the impact
of the active inference research and
also we have correct and incorrect
examples for human and for AI Learners
to be able to use the terms correctly so
that's what the active inference
ontology looks like and there's a few
cool ways that we can just briefly cover
that we use the ontology every day so
one is in the active inference textbook
group where if you come across an
equation like this you might be really
familiar with what variational free
energy is or you might not be but what's
really helpful is to have those
equations written out using the active
inference ontology so that you can Mouse
over to get more definitions and really
just read it out and so this can also be
translated across those different
languages and supports for example
differences in notation amongst
different papers that might be talking
about the same ontology term
but using different letters or symbols
to represent it so that's one way that
we use the ontology when we're adding
value to Publications and textbooks to
connect ideas across different citations
read between the lines and just
understand active inference better
we also
do a lot of philosophy in ontology
project not just is ontology an area of
philosophy but we have explored along
with many others over the last months
ways in which we can use the ontology to
take a procedural approach towards
addressing philosophical questions like
asking about how different topics are
related to each other or whether one
author's perspective on one term is uh
equivalent or dissonance from another
author's perspective on a given term so
these are the kinds of things that we
often find ourselves wondering about
that we often hear beginners asking
about and the ontology helps us give it
deflationary and really action-oriented
way to address these kinds of topics
lastly in this video before everyone
else is here can add any other thoughts
or comments or the areas of contribution
so here's just some of the ways that
people can contribute to this open
source resource and really make a big
difference in the active inference
ecosystem first
with respect to translations
you could add a language that you're
familiar with if it hasn't been added
and if you know a language that has been
added but it's not complete or perfect
you're always welcome to check over
those languages and try to improve them
so currently again the languages that we
have are shown here
with respect to the definitions examples
and connections amongst different
ontology terms everyone would always be
welcome to contribute their attention
and care to reviewing definitions for
accuracy and completeness adding
examples and counter examples
and also adding connections with any
words that one might like just like in
the dictionary where it gives a
definition in terms of other words and
then provides an example that helps
provide context we can add different
connections like that
for those who are interested in some of
the formal computational aspects of
ontology
we're working with the suggested upper
merged ontology so if you're curious or
familiar with sumo or sueo Kiff the
knowledge interchange format then there
are is some later work down the road
that would be awesome to collaborate on
already
in terms of the ontology
uh composition
we're always interested to be able to
review and revise the core terms are
there any terms that we have in the core
set that might not be so important and
are there any terms that you think are
really important for understanding
active inference speaking about it
fluently but are not being included in
the core right now well that is a great
way to help
and
you're always welcome to add different
citations or references to where the
ontology is being used in the wild
using ontology there's a ton of
different use cases that people have
proposed and some are following through
on
analyzing textbooks and other papers
whether written in English or other
language can really make clear the value
of the ontology for those who might see
this as just like a
hypertrophied word list or something
like that
and there's a special focus on the
active inference researcher as well as
the learner and the beginner so what are
the questions and guides and how can we
think about this in terms of the
educational Productions and what makes
learning active inference as a language
really fun and accessible
currently we publish through Coda as
well as through GitHub however this is
not necessarily the
um best possible publication approach
for an ontology so we would look to
those who have expertise in ontology in
this project in a variety of places but
also to help think about how to publish
this in a cool open science way
and then there's a ton of discussion
topics that we're always looking to
develop the status of communicating the
active inference ontology not unlike
this video but how it can be used is
honestly super exciting and there's a
lot to learn and there's a lot to do for
people who even have a little bit of
familiarity with active inference and
even a little bit of time so hopefully
that's you or more so hopefully you do
participate in the ontology project
people have discussed sharing the active
inference ontology in the wild with
people who are using the terms for
example if a term is being misused or
being used in one way or another then
following up on that thread or sending a
communication to that speaker and
letting them know about the terms usage
in the active inference ontology maybe
even inviting them to continue the
collaboration in the project
just could be something cool something
someone's brought up
integration with knowledge engineering
we've performed literature meta-analysis
and used the ontology to guide term and
topic analysis and there's a lot more
work that can be done with
curating across the literature and
across the transcripts of live streams
and understanding where and how the
active infantology makes a difference
there would be a lot of awesome work to
explore with education with learning
groups and projects but also with
development of curriculum materials for
active inference and the last one listed
here is going beyond the examples and
the counter examples but stories and
anti-stories and really just connecting
this work of the active inference
ontology to the topics and the systems
of interest that we discuss every day
so there's also more things you might
want to do we just try to give a really
quick overview of the project itself and
a few of the places where we're going
Dave or Paula would you have any
comments or what else would you like to
add or anything that was sort of just
glossed over before
fine
Dave
no that's clear thank you all right
thanks we hope that you uh get in touch
with active inference gmail.com or find
us elsewhere and we'll see you in the
ontology project thank you